Finding aid to the Nina Elizabeth Browne Papers CA.MS.00384
Smith College Archives
Nina Elizabeth Browne Papers
1860-1956
1878 - 1954
Smith College Archives
Browne, Nina Elizabeth, 1860 - 1954
CA.MS.00384
0.208 linear feet (1 container)
Class of 1882. Librarian. Founder of the College Archives. Collection cContains news clippings, correspondence, essays, photographs, publications, and financial records documenting the student and professional experiences of Nina Browne.
Biographical / Historical
Nina Elizabeth Browne was born in 1860 in Erving, Massachusetts. She received her A.B. from Smith College in 1882, her A.M. in 1885. After teaching for a year she went on to the newly established School of Library Economy at Columbia College (now Columbia University) on the recommendation of a former classmate. The school was established in 1887 by Melvil Dewey, then the chief university librarian. Browne later noted that "when the trustees decided to have the library school, no one of them had a notion that women would come. Because women came, that rule forbidding a woman to enter a classroom forced Mr. [Melvil] Dewey to find a place for the newcomers. He found it in this old building hitherto used as a storeroom."
Columbia did not grant degrees to the classes prior to 1889 and the library program was moved to the University of the State of New York (now SUNY Albany). After being appointed State Librarian of New York in 1889, Dewey petitioned the university to offer a test to graduates from his early classes which required submitting to sixteen proficiency examinations, a compiled subject bibliography, and a thesis. Browne and one other student were the sole participants of this program. Browne was awarded a Bachelor of Library Science from the university in 1891.
She returned to Massachusetts and became an assistant librarian at Harvard and the Boston Athenaeum while working unofficially for the Smith College Alumna Association. A highly active advocate, she served as the Registrar for the American Library Association, compiling their portrait index and travelling to London for the International Conference of Librarianship.
In 1921, Smith College hired Brown as the first Archivist of the College in anticipation of the 50th anniversary of the founding of the college. Much of the initial collection was acquired by Browne's mother during her daughter's time as a Smith student. Although the 50th anniversary project was completed in 1925, Browne continued to build and develop the historical collection. Active well into her 90s, she received her Litt.D. 1930. Partial blindness forced her retirement in 1937. Browne did not leave the position immediately; she continued to advocate the importance of a college archive and argued for a physical space. Margaret Storrs Grierson, then a professor, assisted Browne during this transition before ultimately being appointed the first College Archivist by Elizabeth Morrow in 1940. Browne passed away in 1954 at the Trinity Church Home in Jamaica Plain at the age of 94.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains material documenting the student experiences of Nina Elizabeth Brown, Class of 1882, including undergraduate course work and photographs. The majority of her collection is dedicated to documenting Browne's professional life as a librarian and includes impressions of her experiences at Columbia College Library School [1887 - 1889]. This includes professional and personal correspondence, news clippings, financial records, obituaries, publications and research.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Related Materials
Additional material may be found in the following collections:
Buildings Records, 1875 - ongoing
Class of 1882 Records, 1876 - 1959
Katherine Elizabeth McClellan Papers, 1879 - 1996
Margaret Storrs Grierson Papers, 1800 - 1900 [bulk 1918 - 1997]
10.9 History of Smith College Archives and Sophia Smith Collection
Library schools and training; Smith College - Alumni and alumnae - History - Sources; Women librarians - United States; American Library Association - History; Browne, Nina E. (Nina Eliza), 1860 - 1954; Columbia University. School of Library Economy; Dewey, Melvil, 1851-1931; McClellan, Katherine Elizabeth; Smith College - History - Sources
- Smith College Archives, 1921-1940 (Box 689, Folder 1)
- library assistant, 1916-1917, 1882-1956 (Box 689, Folder 2)
- correspondence, 1896-1947 (Box 689, Folder 3)
- correspondence - Jackson, Annie Brown, 1902-1903 (Box 689, Folder 4)
- correspondence - McClellan, D.G., 1936-1949 (Box 689, Folder 5)
- correspondence - round robin letters to the Class of 1882 (Box 689, Folder 6)
- degrees, 1883-1930 (Box 689, Folder 7)
- financial records, 1920-1949 (Box 689, Folder 8)
- photographs, 1882-1952 (Box 689, Folder 9)
- publications - "My First ALA", 1945-1946 (Box 689, Folder 10)
- publications - "Reminiscences of the First Library School of Columbia University", 1887-1937 (Box 689, Folder 11)
- publications - "Reflections and Memoirs", 1900-1946 (Box 689, Folder 12)
- undergraduate papers, 1878-1882 (Box 689, Folder 13)